A tough cop. A brilliant killer. An unspeakable crime.
Insomnia is a thriller, crime, drama film directed by Christopher Nolan.
Two Los Angeles homicide detectives are dispatched to a northern town where the sun
doesn't set to investigate the methodical murder of a local teen.
Will Dormer, played by Al Pacino.
Walter Finch, played by Robin Williams.
Ellie Burr, played by Hilary Swank.
Hap Eckhart, played by Martin Donovan.
Fred Duggar, played by Nicky Katt.
Rachel Clement, played by Maura Tierney.
Insomnia is a 2002 American neo-noir psychological thriller film directed by Christopher Nolan and written by
Hillary Seitz; it is the only film directed by Nolan that he is not credited with writing.
A remake of the 1997 Norwegian film, it stars Al Pacino, Robin Williams, and Hilary Swank, with
Maura Tierney, Martin Donovan, Nicky Katt, and Paul Dooley in supporting roles.
The film follows two Los Angeles homicide detectives
investigating a murder in Nightmute, Alaska.
After the killer witnesses an accidental shooting committed by one of the detectives,
they create a plan for both parties to mutually avoid prosecution.
Insomnia premiered at the Tribeca Festival on May 3, 2002, and was
theatrically released in the United States and Canada on May 24, 2002.
It grossed $113.8 million worldwide against a production budget of $46 million.
The film received positive reviews, with praise for
Pacino's and Williams's performances.
At the 29th Saturn Awards, Williams was nominated for Best
Supporting Actor, and Seitz was nominated for Best Writing.
The film explores themes of hotel, small town, homicide, confession, blackmail.
The tone is dark and emotional and intense.